welcome to meditating
with john vervicky so
i have an announcement to begin
everything with
um we will continue the live streaming
at 9 30 a.m eastern time for the rest of
this week
but then we'll have to switch to a
weekly schedule
because we're going back to work we're
going back to school as part of the
stage three reopening
uh jason and amara and i have had
several conversations about trying to
get
our schedules to intersect so that we
could do a daily
uh meeting a daily session and we just
can't make it work
uh so what we're going to do is we'll
finish the rest of this week
um at the daily uh sessions at 9 30 a.m
eastern
and not this saturday but the following
saturday
not this saturday but the following
saturday we will switch to going to
weekly saturday mornings at 10 30 a.m
for an hour
we will go from 10 30 a.m to 11 30 a.m
eastern time saturday morning sorry
everyone i know that's a bit of a jar
we we just recently came to this
conclusion all of our schedules are just
gelling now
and this is what we're going to need to
do going forward
i sincerely hope and i encourage uh
people to
the second to continue to meet regularly
daily on the discord server
and do the daily practice and saturday
will always therefore
be a dharma day and we will have uh
that's why we're going to do an hour
class and we will switch we will start
by
sitting on saturdays first uh we'll sit
and then we'll do the dharma day the
dharma lesson
and then we'll take a q a so that's the
schedule we're going to switch to
um i believe it'll be something like the
13th or something i'll get the exact
date for you tomorrow
but it is not this saturday it is the
following saturday
if you're joining us for this first time
uh you're most welcome
please know that i think this is the
108th class we've met
all the previous classes have been
recorded both the lessons and the sits
you're most welcome to continue to meet
with us i recommend
see the description for this video and
you'll find links to the lessons do
lesson one right away
and then work your way through try to do
two lessons a week uh
meet with us on saturdays for the dharma
days meet on the discord server with the
signup
to do the regular sets at the end of
this session
um on the end of every session that we
will be meeting
even when we go to the new such the new
schedule uh there will be a q a period
please limit the questions at that time
to anything from the entire ecology of
practice either the eastern traditions
or the western wisdom traditions for
more general questions we will still be
holding our live streamed general q a
on youtube every third friday of the
month at 3 p.m eastern time
so yesterday uh was a large lesson
i'm going to let people sit with it for
the week and then i will review it again
on friday and take some q a at that time
uh please be patient with us also we are
trying out some new technology so that
we can make use of two cameras uh during
the lessons
so that we don't have to move the
cameras around when we move from the
sitting
to using the whiteboard uh so we're just
working out
um some bugs on that and jason and amar
are working furiously
uh behind the scenes for us though we
can just sit
so what i'd ask everybody to do is to
get themselves in position
set their phones on do not deserve we
will begin together
uh when when i say begin we will start
with some
chanting and then we will go into our
sonnet sit
and then we'll take some questions and i
encourage people in addition to
questions to sharing comments
notifications concerns etc
all right begin
oh
one
[Music]
um
one
[Music]
on
one
begin your silences
[Music]
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness
cognition character and communitas
perhaps by reciting
the five promises
so
well we have time for a couple of
questions
first one from mark always good to see
you mark
uh excellent time on the discord server
last night
and mark asked a fantastic question
about addiction and sort of in a
three-stage way
i tried to answer at length as best i
can that was very very
powerful exchange between us
mark asks here what practices do you
think help make the peritonic mode
salient is this just contemplation or is
it more involved
so the best way to
uh get into the peritonic mode
so chicks have a high call says flow is
autotellic and autotelic is basically
synonymous with peritolic so those
practices
uh that get you into the flow state uh
will get you more and more aware of
the peritonic mode in fact
i think uh the flow state uh i remember
we talked about the flow state can
you know is on a continuum from sort of
you know mild to medium to intense but
all good
i think the flow state um is in fact a
marker
of of that mode um because that is the
mode
uh in which we are going through the
most developmental
uh change because that's what the
peritelic mode's about it's about where
we play
in order to develop as opposed to
vitalik mode
where we work in order to survive
so i think any of the practices
that get you into the flow state of
course they would be contemplative
practices
uh but the movement practices can also
get you into that but many uh you know
many of the things that
have been created precisely because um
they generate the flow state playing
jazz
writing poetry all of these things
notice how a lot of these are the arts
and our work
obsessed workaholic culture that works
us to death for nothing other than
working so that we can continue to work
to make it
make it possible for other people to
work
has of course denigrated the arts
because
they though those principles that move
us in that way have forgotten those
principles and powers that move us that
way
have forgotten the being mode modal
confusion
and they have forgotten how important
the serious play of art
is to remembering sati
the being mode remembering the peritonic
mode
because that is the mode in which human
beings
most activate their devel and actualize
their developmental potential
and thereby most afford their
aspirational
growth so i think it's very important
that we deepen and extend mark's
question
into asking ourselves not only what are
the practices but how can we
incorporate more of them into our lives
in a more comprehensive and integrated
fashion
so uh karima cynthia clayton
there's a question socrates and plato
taught that knowledge gained in past
lives is the basis for education in the
present life
what happened that the epicureans
dropped the belief
um so it's not clear if socrates
believes that
socrates in the apology very clearly
states
uh that he has no knowledge of the
afterlife
um and um and that therefore he
should in no way fear it or hope for it
plato of course is deeply influenced by
the pythagoreans
and i agree with a lot of the research
that argues that the pythagoreans
were influenced by shamanism and
shamanism of course
has the idea of soul flight and
reincarnation
the epicureans drop it because they
are not as influenced by plato
they are more directly influenced by
socrates
and because they also have a much more
scientific bent of mind
they didn't think that the psyche the
soul
was immaterial they thought it was also
made up of atoms special kind of atom
and therefore like everything else made
of atoms it would dissipate
given enough time that caused them
problems of course with respect
to the existence and the immortality of
the gods and the epicureans
they give some of the first arguments in
history for what you might call
atheism arguments the argument that's
often attributed to hume
you know if the gods are all powerful
and all good why is there
evil actually originates with epicurus
so there was a questioning in the
epicureans of a lot
of what you might call the pythagorean
and shamanic
aspects that plato introduced in
um now neoplatonism uh does follow uh
those aspects neoplatonism picks up
again
uh the ideas of rebir reincarnation past
lives
and such but that's sort of the
historical answer to your question
karima
ah rawat yonas slow reading precious
speaking
intentional conversing ruminatio i'm
wondering i forgot the order of
practices correctly
uh no it goes slow reading and then
ruminatio i believe precious speaking
and then intentional conversing
so i that's how it should be uh let me
make sure
that's how it should be now let me make
sure i'll check my notes
that that's what i presented um
yesterday
you know you do the slow reading you do
the room and out the other chanting then
there's the precious speaking
and then you take that into uh the
intentional
conversing um uh kiera kroger
welcome kyra i haven't heard from you in
a bit it's good to hear from you again
question i understand the reasoning for
avoiding automaticity and authority in
the practice we talked about yesterday
but i don't understand the reason for
avoiding
autobiography can you elaborate yes the
the the
the reason for avoiding autobiography is
that people fall into making the
practice
about um extending reflecting on getting
feedback getting validation
uh for their autobiography and so
um i understand your concern it's like
well how do i make it
relevant but
what i'm asking you to do is
i think this is the right way of putting
it trust your relevance realization
machinery
your ego anyone's ego not just yours in
particular
you know saying unless you keep spinning
my autobiographical web
um you won't realize the relevance of
things and of course that's
um the flow state is overwhelming
evidence the meditative states are
overwhelming evidence
that your relevance realization
machinery making things relevant
is not going to conk out in fact it's
probably going to be
developed and accentuated when you leave
off
um autobiography so one of the things
that's difficult
in all of these practices is
to get people to break the monologue of
autobiography
because that's what autobiography is
you're talking about yourself and you're
largely talking to yourself
you're trying to break when we all do it
i'm not accusing anybody of anything
we have to break the frame of monologue
so that we become genuinely open to
dialogue
and trust that our relevance realization
machinery will continue to work and work
in fact
better in dialogue and so
i know that's that's that's something
i'm asking you to trust and to try
but what i can say is um
i have good reason and confidence to
believe
that if you make this move you will find
it
uh deeply rewarding kiera kroger in my
practice i noticed a deep sadness at the
loss of the daily
meditation classes i i know kara we
we we struggled to try i i
we are all felt very responsible to this
um
and we we've tried many times uh you
know i just tried to find intersections
we were thinking of doing some evening
classes
i just just can't get it to work
and so i'm hoping
that i will still
be able to answer a lot of questions
uh give you some reliable sense
of my presence
in your lives as a teacher and mentor
with the saturday morning dharma class
um it's we're we're we're kind of
switching more to the
you know uh you know the synagogue
temple mosque
church model where we meet once a week
and it's it's a longer
time and always there's always some
dharma
and so that has worked for people
obviously in many contexts across many
generations
within many religious frameworks this is
not a religious framework but
you understand the analogy i i'm making
and so i'm hoping that will continue to
work and i
am hoping and i'm encouraged by the
by the belief that uh the discord server
can take
over the function of homing uh the
weekly senga
and giving a place where people can
still
review the lessons all of the lessons
are are recorded
people can still meet they can still
review they can still practice
there's no real reason for the weekly
meetings to stop
and i'm going to do my best to try and
maintain perhaps not as extensive but
hopefully
a significant presence as a teacher and
mentor
for the sangha so i share your sadness
it has can it has been very nourishing
and meaningful to me
but um we
this is the best we the best response
we've been able to come up with
so remi remember the rest of the week is
as normal
we are not not meeting this saturday
but the following saturday we will move
to the weekly schedule
so we will not be meeting next week
during the weekdays
but we will start next week on the
saturday
for an hour 10 am to 11am
eastern time i want to thank you all for
joining um
and joining me throughout all of this
um who knows how things unfold we may be
back again
in a different way under a lockdown
i hope not i hope that these things can
are progressing
uh quite well in canada um
i don't think things are going to go
back to the way they were before covet
i think that's a false hope
but i do think we're going through yet
another transition and we're trying to
work out
a new way of being and so i ask
everybody to adapt
and i ask you to trust
in the practices
that we have shared together and learned
together
to affording your capacities for
transformation
and adaptivity as we go through yet
another phase
together and we will be going through it
together we're not going away
we're just going to be differently
present
so amar and jason have been working
really hard to get
this new technology working that way
when we switch
uh to the saturdays and we're doing
the dharma classes we will be able to
cut between cameras and record that for
everybody
make that available we won't be doing
the weird move moving of the camera and
the weird angle
and so that should hopefully make
everything worse
please subscribe to the channel to be
notified of the next video
also please follow me on twitter twitter
for any updates about this
these streams if you're not opposed to
it on principle
please invite others who might benefit
by sharing this series
i'm i think this is a virtuous way of
saying this
i'm very proud of this series i'm very
proud of what we have done together
very proud of it it's one of the best
things i've done
in my life and i thank you all for that
tremendously please it's very important
now
this is no longer just an addition or an
amendment it's very important that we
join the discord server that's how the
saying is going to continue that's how
the practices are going to continue
that's the place where you're going to
be able to find a home
for philosophical contemplative
companionships and they're going to be
really i think a vital way of adding to
the vibrance the vibrancy and the
vitality
of the sanghas communitas
so we'll be continuing to meet at 9 30
a.m eastern
time for wednesday and thursday and
friday of this week
lastly please remember now more than
ever
continuity of practice is more important
than sheer quantity of practice
don't hold yourself to the standard of
hearth's perfectionism
hold yourself to the standard of
virtuous friendship
because there is no enemy worse than
your own mind and body
there is no friend no ally
no true contemplative companion on the
path better than your own minded body
be lamps onto yourselves and to each
other
i'll see you all tomorrow take good care
everyone
are we out